All right,
meeting is started and I'm gonna go ahead
and admit everybody just take a second,
all right?
And we should be good to start.
Great.
Good morning, everyone.
My name is Porter Gonzalez.
I'm the Medical Psilocyber Program
Manager.
We have Ian Dunn,
who's the Chair of our Advisory Board and
also of this patient Qualification and
Safety Committee.
So we'll start in just a moment.
Just to remind you that this meeting is
being recorded.
So Please remember to keep language
appropriate as the recordings are made
public on the Advisory Board website.
And with that,
our cameras are usually off because in
the far regions and frontiers and rural
areas of New Mexico that, you know,
using camera can,
the bandwidth is decreased.
And so we do keep cameras off.
Ian will have his camera on and when you
have an opportunity to speak,
we will have time for them.
And I'll put those instructions into the
chat.
So with that, Ian, take it away.
Good morning, everyone.
I'll call this meeting of the Patient
Qualification and Safety Committee to
order.
Just a reminder,
committees operate in an advisory
capacity to provide forum to people who
may have perceived or real conflicts of
interest.
They provide they support the board by
providing expanded community input.
I just wanted to welcome everyone today
is not anything specific.
Usually I come with a document.
I wanted to allow open discussion on
other patient safety areas.
So for instance, we have,
I adopted a lot of the qualification what
it,
what safety thresholds do you need to
meet to be a patient,
But we haven't talked about other aspects
of patient safety.
Those can include informed consent,
environmental safety and other aspects.
So I just wanted to hear from the
committee about what, you know,
they thought we needed to work on next in
regards to that.
So I will turn to any hands if anyone
would like to speak and introduce
themselves.
All right.
And to raise your hand on Teams,
there is a icon with a hand that says
raise under it in the top banner.
Its exact location can depend sometimes
from computer to computer and system to
system.
But if you find that raise icon with the
hand,
if you are welcome to click on that and
then we will pawn you in order.
Oh, and yeah,
and you can also introduce yourself in
the chat or put any comments or questions
in there as well.
Perfect.
And we did get an introduction in the
chat from James Brown,
Farm DA Veteran of New Mexico 5° N
Healing Foundation,
already with no other introductory
comments.
I had prepared some work on informed
consent in the event that there was no
specific comments from the committee,
if you wouldn't mind opening that
document for me.
So what happened was this informed
consent basically was taken straight from
what the dosage Administration and
Clinical Practice Committee had been
working on.
It actually technically falls under our
jurisdiction to adopt the informed
consent.
So I just wanted to go ahead and review
it here as well.
Just so we can make sure you know,
we were all on the same page.
So,
for psilocybin informed consent before
undergoing psilocybin assisted therapy,
informed consent must be obtained from
both the facilitator and patient.
Informed consent should be obtained
through direct discussion and shall not
solely be satisfied by written
acknowledgement.
The discussion shall include risks,
benefits, uncertainties,
altered states of consciousness,
and impaired decision making.
The department shall create a
standardized informed consent form
notifying the patient what psilocybin is.
Overview of psilocybin treatment.
Possible side slash adverse effects
associated with treatment benefits of
psilocybin use In a statement
acknowledging the that the use of
psilocybin has not been approved by the
FDA to treat or cure any condition.
Any other additions?
Comments, questions,
Concerns about informed consent?
What we can add?
All righty, then we'll move.
Oh, James.
All right.
And I have enabled your mic, James,
so you can unmute when ready.
Morning, Ian and everyone on this one.
Ian, do we have a section here?
I'm not sure if you have it in the future
that talks about, you know,
I'm just looking at other consents that
are out there and I'm saying receive
participants consent and decisions
related to the safety plan,
the physical touch and the presence of
any other individuals.
Is that in this part or is that somewhere
else we're going to cover?
We can include it here If we want to just
make the informed consent broader,
I think that would be within our scope to
do.
Can you just enter really quickly into
the chat what you said so I can copy it
over?
Will do.
I'll put it in real quick.
Perfect.
All right,
looks like James dropped that in the chat.
Perfect.
And then so supportive touch.
Absolutely.
What were you like what specifically
whether we should allow it,
whether we should not I believe in dosage.
We were working on saying like in
emergency,
in emergency situations where like you
have to obtain vitals or do any of those
things that we were going to allow it.
So did you want to just kind of
incorporate similar language or what was
your thoughts on that?
Yeah, exactly.
And something to that extent, you know,
we use a participant consent, you know,
for that supportive touch.
And are your still thoughts around the
shoulders, hands and feet?
Is that what your kind of thought was
Besides the emergency touch of you're
gonna prevent somebody from falling,
you're gonna have to catch them or,
you know,
you might have to support them in a
different way than just touching their
shoulder.
If they're, you know,
if they're gonna be at harm, so are you.
It's two different things.
Are you thinking individual emergency
supportive touch?
We need something with that as well as a
just what's your thought on that?
Just that general consent Thoughts.
Yeah.
So I would be OK with getting their
consent for supportive touch.
I think it can be especially useful with
some of the emotionalness that can come
from psychedelic therapy.
And sometimes human contact can really
bridge that internal sense of safety.
So I do think that it can be allowed
should discuss supportive touch generally.
Hands.
You said hands, shoulders, the.
OK,
So patient and facilitators should
discuss supportive touch.
Generally, hands,
shoulders and feet are appropriate.
All right.
And I see Kate Hawk's hand up.
And Kate, I have loud your mic.
You can unmute.
Yeah.
Good morning, everybody.
This is Kate.
I'm looking at this and it's, you know,
looks fine, is general,
but then of course it mentions the
standardized informed consent form.
And I'm wondering, you know,
it feels like the discussion of exactly
what touch is approved and what isn't.
You know, I'm I'm just wondering,
has there been an in depth discussion of
that?
Are we just looking at, well,
here's what Colorado does and you know,
so it feels like the informed consent
form would have more details or maybe
there's a further discussion.
And I want to mention that here in Santa
Fe,
we're going to have a meeting of just a
couple of really dinner salon meetings
with one for therapists and one for
facilitators.
And so these kind of questions about
touch are important.
So, you know,
other states don't allow really bodywork
or other things that could be helpful.
So I just want to make sure we're
considering all of these things carefully.
Yeah.
And I do appreciate that's why I tried to
word it very loosely with the supportive
touch.
So I definitely think they should support,
they should discuss supportive touch.
What is OK with each person is going to
vary.
So I said generally hand shoulders would
be are appropriate.
But if your practice has a policy of
saying, well, we typically do this,
are you OK with that?
That would be fine.
We're just saying in general care,
these are kind of the like what we would
see in Colorado and that kind of thing.
If you did want to go further,
I wouldn't restrict that as long as there
was patient and facilitator consent is my
opinion.
But I would love to hear from the
committee as well.
Yeah, that makes sense.
And, you know, looking down the line,
what kind of questions would come up.
I know,
I know we're doing the best to have
clarity and not unnecessary limitations,
but, you know, to be clear.
So that's all I have to say for now.
Thank you.
All right.
Yeah.
And then Anne Met said in the chat or
actually let me read a couple of chats.
Catherine Warnock said,
what if someone wants a hug?
I feel this is too limiting.
And then Anne said other states
distinguish between safety and supportive
touch.
People must consent to safety touch,
but supportive touch is optional.
Yeah, absolutely.
That's why we,
at least in the dosage side,
'cause they're doing kind of the
preparation and clinical practice side,
which would be the like safety planning
and that kind of part of preparation.
They said, you know,
if it's an emergency and we have to.
Like if it's an emergency,
they have to get vitals,
they're going to be allowed to obviously
get the vitals and make sure that they're
safe.
This is just more so that's supportive
kind of if it helps them emotionally.
And then we have a thing from Catherine
Warnock saying maybe also specify that
all touch is non sexual.
I did go ahead and add that Eileen Brewer
said it's definitely a difficult topic.
I know there's a bunch of emerging
evidence that physical therapy during a
psychedelic experience might be
beneficial, and that's why I said it.
They should,
the facilitator and the participant
should discuss that.
I think different facilitators are going
to offer different skills.
If one of them is trained in, you know,
physical therapy or or is educated on it
and wants to perform that as well,
that should be offered to the patient.
But it is ultimately the patient and
facilitators collective consent on what
is, you know, done in that regard.
And then Eileen added a couple more chats.
I think getting rid of generally hands,
feet and hand shoulders and feet are
appropriate might be wise.
My quotes are in the wrong place are no
worries.
It's it's a Monday, we all understand.
Yeah, So we can get rid of that.
The reason it's included is just 'cause
that's what they are doing in other
states.
If you guys want to,
if that's overwhelming consensus to
remove it, that would be fine with me.
Does anyone else have thoughts on whether
that generally provision generally hands,
shoulders and feet are appropriate should
be removed?
Participants session OK Should we allow
that both ways?
So like if a participant or a facilitator
may withdraw their consent to receiving
supportive touch at any time,
or should we just keep it as participants?
Perfect.
All righty.
And then probably both from James Brown
and then Eileen Brewer said I agree.
Participant or facilitator.
And yeah,
that is what I went ahead and add.
Patients and facilitators retain the
right to withdraw their consent for
support of touch at any time during the
session.
Just patient.
I think it's important for the patient to
rely on.
OK, so we do have a little bit,
I do see James's hand up.
So I will go ahead and let him speak.
Ian and group, you know,
and I'm all up for more touch and and
understanding the difference between,
you know,
allowing the participants and and again,
I just want to emphasize that piece,
Ian and everyone that this is for the
individual.
Yes,
there's other modalities and treatments
that we can use,
which I would love to see incorporated
while you're doing your journey or
experience or having your individual
patient going through that experience.
It can open up different things in the
mind.
It can really help that DMN zone,
you know,
to really help that default mode network.
Some of these other modalities help to
tap into those resources.
And we're just finding out exactly what
things you can do.
Meditation activities, painting,
journalism, whatever.
That patient might just be sitting there
meditating in their spiritual focus,
you know,
while they're going through that.
And that just opens up different things.
And so touch is important.
And so I just didn't want us to constrict
so much on touch.
I just want us to have something that's
really informed on what touch is gonna be
and what touch is not gonna be.
And then and then go from there and maybe
open up those modalities.
But again,
the focus is that individuals experience
and treatment.
So I just want to make sure we're
focusing as much on, you know,
not the person doing stuff for them
because we're just going to be there for
them to support them,
but really what that individual needs to
do themselves to heal.
Thank you.
Yeah, thank you.
So I do think it it is important for what
we can do for the patient.
The reason I wanted to include the right
of facilitators to retain the right to
withdrawal is there's a lot of instances
of,
there can be instances of patients acting
inappropriately.
And I also want to make sure that our
facilitators are safe.
I do think that patients overwhelmingly
are great,
but just because there are those one off
instances,
I think that they should retain their
right to withdraw.
So I completely agreed.
Did you want me to just strike this?
Generally hands, feet,
and shoulders are appropriate then to
allow for those other modalities as
evidence becomes more abundant.
What about use examples of or something
like that to give them a basis of ideas?
I don't know, thoughts.
All right.
So I said, for instance, hands,
feet and shoulders, hand,
shoulders and feet are generally
appropriate.
This acts more to say like these are some
examples of what's generally appropriate.
However, you know,
even within different cultural contexts,
what is acceptable to a person in terms
of physical touch are different.
So that's going to give that room for
what is what each facilitator and what
each patient come to agreement on.
But in terms does anyone else think this
informed consent needs any other
additions or changes or really any
comment you have on it?
All right,
then we will just go ahead and move to
adoption of this informed consent for the
Patient qualification and Safety
committee.
All those in favor,
please raise your hand at this time.
Hold OK,
save three hands up or if you include the
chair, all hands down, please.
All right.
And then if you are against,
please raise your hand.
I see no hands with four to zero.
This is adopted.
There should also be in the drafts folder
of the Patient qualification Safety
committee,
there's an environmental safety document.
Is that in this month's,
I mean this current folder?
So go into committees,
patient qualification safety and then
drafts.
OK, Environmental safety, yes, OK.
And then I won't know.
I know I'm going to go.
I just need to go drop you going.
I just have to go drop off milk and then
I have an 11:00.
All right,
so let's begin discussion on emergency
preparation.
So I've also posted the at least the
emergency preparation part in the chat.
This is just to ensure that all
facilities are, you know,
adequate for psilocybin therapy.
It basically states that each treatment
area shall have a minimum of two
accessible exits.
Exits shall be clearly marked and
unobstructed.
Facilities shall not use locked barriers
that prevent rapid exit except we're
clinically justified and compliant with
applicable law.
Facilities shall maintain reliable means
of communication to activate emergency
medical services at all times.
All facilities shall maintain a random
emergency response plan appropriate to
the level of services provided in patient
risk.
The plan must include procedures for
medical and behavioral emergencies.
Clearly finds after roles and timely
activation of emergency medical services
facilities that are not reasonably
accessible to emergency services or that
provide services to higher risk pension.
Maintain enhanced emergency response
capabilities come comensurate with the
level of risk we're permitted under state
law and overseen by a licensed provider
with prescriptive authority.
This may include the availability of
emergency medications and appropriate
monitoring equipment.
Does anyone have any questions, comments,
concerns on that emergency preparation?
Anne,
I just am thinking about people who work
in therapy offices that maybe don't have
two exits.
You know,
some of us work in old buildings.
So that would be my one concern.
You know,
I wonder if there's just a way to, yeah,
I can understand why that would be sort
of a good general rule,
but I think kind of in practice,
when people work in old Adobe buildings
that have no closets and have one door,
that that is a limitation that maybe
isn't necessary.
All right.
And then Katherine Warnock in the chat
also said she agreed.
I don't have two exits in my building
either.
So I would be OK with,
should we allow it to defer it to
deference and say a reasonable number of
accessible exits for the number of
patients being served?
Gregory.
Hey, good morning.
Sorry I came in late.
The my name is Gregory Evans in the
propagation committee.
This was kind of handled by building
inspection and like the fire like so when
you get your license you're required to
follow certain parameters for that
license.
One of those is building expense, build,
building inspection for the permit to
operate a business and if we just divert
it to the parameters of what your county
or your specific area deems whatever you
get what I'm saying my brain.
Yeah like by occupancy and exit.
Yeah that way it's not our responsibility.
It's written into like the code of yeah
whatever.
Then I would actually bringing up.
That's a really good point.
I'd be actually good with just striking
this and then letting the municipalities
work it out.
And you're not the only one with a
mundane brain, Eileen.
I've.
The number of umms I've said in this call
is outrageous.
But Raymond had his hand up.
Yeah, I'm here.
Can you hear me?
Yep.
OK,
So I'm gonna go ahead and reinforce that
one of the things that we're looking at
is all of this stuff that pertains to
occupancy and building codes and fire
codes and all that are gonna fall to the
local municipal agency.
That makes it the easiest because as long
as they're in compliance with their local
fire codes,
we don't have to worry about that as long
as they have their certificate of
occupancy,
which means they're going to have to get
their fire inspections done and things
like that.
So occupancy for municipalities is
generally based on, you know,
how many people are there,
how many exits are available?
Like some of them actually cover restroom
facilities and things like that.
So when it comes to the physical building
parts of it,
I believe our intent was to leave that to
the, like I said,
the local municipal government to
regulate that.
Now in the Fed,
in the event that there is no laws or
statutes or things like that,
I don't think it's it would be wrong of
us to provide guidance.
But I don't think this is anything that
we're going to look at enforcing other
than whether or not they possess that
certificate.
Cool.
Then the only thing we should maintain
our emergency preparedness plans and
communication, right?
When it, when it, when it,
when it pertains to the patient and
things like that.
Yes.
But as far as the building codes, parking,
you know, electrical, water,
all that's gonna that's gonna be up to
them to make sure that they're in
compliance with their local government.
Do most municipalities prevent locked
barriers that prevent rapid exit?
I believe most do.
If it's a business,
we'd have to look into the details of
that.
I don't,
I don't want to say that there is and
then find out that there's one county
that doesn't.
But in in most instances,
if it's a business that's open,
there has to be accessible fire exits.
OK, I'm going to go ahead and strike that.
Let me know at the next meeting if that
was wrong.
So we'll just keep that.
Facility shall maintain reliable means of
communication to activate emergency
medical services at all times.
All facilities shall maintain a written
emergency response plan appropriate to
the level services provided and patient
risk plan must include procedures for
medical and behavioral emergencies,
clearly defined staff roles,
and timely activation of emergency
medical services.
Facilities that are not reasonably
reasonably accessible to emergency
medical services or that provide services
to higher risk patients shall maintain
enhanced emergency response capabilities
commensurate with the level of risk where
permitted under state law and overseen by
a licensed provider with prescriptive
authority.
This may include the availability of
emergency medications and appropriate
monitoring equipment.
And I see James has his hand up.
Yes, James,
Ian in this is there a section in here,
I'm not sure yet if is there a
transportation plan been completed
section, you know,
in that emergency preparation area.
And then also thought was if,
if are we going to open this up to the to
the home, You know,
if these people are going to be doing end
of life,
are they going to be allowed to be doing
this in their house?
If so,
some of the safety plans need to be a
little less restrictive.
If if we're thinking of somebody's house
versus a business,
all I don't wanna interrupt you,
but all end of life has its own like
completely separate rules.
Great.
OK, Thank you.
Yeah.
So none of this is gonna apply.
I deferred it to their committee because
that's such a specific area and they have
a lot more leeway than the rest of the
program.
So for now,
I've deferred all of those decisions
regarding end of life treatment to the
end of life committee.
Thank you.
And then so just you do we need a
transportation area in here somewhere?
I'm not sure.
Thank you.
I will definitely keep it in mind.
I think it would go,
I think it's already gonna go with the
dosage committee's preparation plan to
have a,
you have to have a ride home essentially.
So I think we don't need it here,
but I will definitely if there is a spot
later, then I will tuck it in there.
All right,
Is everyone good with the emergency
preparedness or preparation?
Jeez, it is a Monday.
Cool.
So this is the part that I have not
thoroughly expanded on.
One to four was taken I believe from
Colorado's maximum or maybe it was organs.
So it fully open to debate and discussion.
But patient for to provider ratio shall
not exceed one to four across all
clinical support tiers.
Ratios may be further restricted based on
individual patient needs,
clinical judgement and level of risk.
High risk patients may or require
additional staffing or clinical presence
as appropriate.
To ensure patient safety.
Patients shall be under continuous
supervision by a facilitator during the
active administration.
Patients shall not be left unintended and
staff shall maintain the ability to
promptly observe or respond to patients
at all times.
So I definitely need some input on the
patient to provide a ratio.
So let's go ahead and start there.
Questions.
Comments, concerns, notes.
Gregory,
I think setting a minimum for patient
provider ratio,
it seems better than setting a maximum.
I think, again,
I know it's going to be deferred to the
specifics of the EOL community,
but there could be many situations where
the desired support team of an individual
doesn't match the clinical 1 to 4
requirement.
Like I like to look at it like birth.
If, you know, I have a doula, a mother,
a mother-in-law,
two other people and a doctor.
It's like we're way past that.
And it should be allowable for a patient
to define.
Me personally,
I don't really want anyone in the room.
But but yeah,
I just think that a ceiling seems strange.
And if the only reason we have that is
because we ripped it from a program in
existence, then I don't know,
maybe you could use some thought.
I'll let the adults speak.
Thank you, Kate.
Yeah.
The the way it's written here sounds like
it's maybe not what we really mean.
You know,
we don't mean like one patient to 4
providers, right?
We're looking at like what?
One provider to four patients maximum.
Is that right?
That is, that is up.
Yep.
Yep, you are.
I'm awake on a Monday.
Hey, you beat us all.
You beat us all.
OK.
You know, having said that,
I do say it's a really important question
about are we going to require more than
one provider per patient, You know,
for like, well,
if they have to go to the bathroom or
something,
somebody going to be left alone for 5
minutes.
But then it on the other side,
it really increases the costs and
accessibility.
So I think that's a very important
question about, you know,
how do we balance those things.
So yes, to clarify what she picked up on,
I had swapped it.
So I had said one patient to 4 providers.
What I met was one like facilitator to
four patients, assuming they were all,
you know, very low risk patients,
they could be 1 to 4.
But thank you so much for helping me
correct that.
Yeah.
And then Catherine, yes, good morning.
Couple things.
The first thing I already kind of posted
it in the chat that I actually think it's
important to always have at least two
providers because if something happens to
one of them,
is it the patient's responsibility to
call 911?
If I think you need to have at least two
people on site, doesn't have to be,
you know,
it could even just be an assistant or an
admin person,
but somebody needs to be present,
not just one facilitator.
And then I also think so I have many
clients who don't want to be attended at
all times.
In fact, it's, you know,
I use call buttons and I check on client,
I check on them every depending on when
you're where you are in the process,
anywhere from 15 to 30 minutes.
I have and and I'm allowing them to have
agency to call me because I want to be
there when they need me,
but I don't want to be interrupting their
experience.
I'm actually thinking about maybe even
having live streaming in the room so that
I can observe them at all times,
but not have to like be on them.
I mean,
there's nothing weirder than especially
somebody who's struggling to lean in
knowing that somebody is staring,
sitting there staring at them.
But I also have clients who want somebody
holding their hand for the majority of
the session.
So I sort of allow the client to decide
that based on where they are in their
journey and what's happening for them.
So I just,
I don't know if we need to like maybe
specify what does not be left unattended
mean.
So anyway, that's my two cents.
Thank you.
Yeah.
And just so for clarification,
that language comes from how nurses are
treated.
It doesn't mean they're in the room with
them 24/7.
It just means like they have the ability
to promptly observe and to respond to the
patient at all times.
So maybe let's change that wording.
So left unattended and then instead of
that, we'll make it a parentheses.
That way it's a definition.
Patient should not be left untended.
Staff shall maintain the ability to
promptly observe or respond to patients
at all times.
That way we don't have to be in the room
with them.
I don't think that is necessary.
I don't think you need someone breathing
down your neck to benefit from this.
But I do think someone should be,
you know, callable, like you said,
with a that call button or, you know,
some communication Ave.
away from needing help.
I just don't want them to like, oh,
they just got dosed and now I have to go
on a lunch break.
So I'm going to leave really quick,
but I'll be back.
That was what I was trying to prevent.
Not that I want them, You know, I yes, I,
I heard about somebody taking their dog
for a walk while a client was dozing.
And I thought, oh, that's not OK.
Yeah.
So not leading the premises, being within,
like, I like the way you worded it,
being able to respond at all times.
That's what I think is key.
So thank you.
But I also still want to go back to the.
I think we need at least few people at
all times.
I just don't think.
Like, I'm all about, you know,
resolving trauma,
not like creating trauma.
And I can only imagine if something like
if the one provider there something
happens to them,
is it the patient's responsibility when
they're under the influence to, you know,
take care of the provider?
It's almost like maybe we need to say
like there needs to be, yeah, there we go.
Because I think 4 to 1 is still a good
ratio when you've got multiple,
but a minimum of two, if that makes sense.
Because a 4 to 2 is really a 2 to one,
right?
So, yeah,
so I think maybe a four to one ratio is
fine.
It's just but a minimum of two.
Yeah, I think that would be great,
Gregory.
I think it's interesting to kind of
understand the difference between our
system and organs.
But because fundamentally it doesn't
appear that we are going to be imposing
fines for violations.
Like the actions are going to be pretty
much like fix it or you're done or
whatever.
But so like that type of like infraction
measurement and Monday isn't yet defined.
But in Oregon like for example.
So I don't think Thomas is in here,
but Intertech last year was fined $3000
for somebody going to the bathroom.
And I don't want to like diminish like
the impact of like the event that's
documented on the OAOHA website.
But yeah, it's like the, the,
the thing about like somebody taking
their dog for a walk,
there's like context missing.
Like,
is that like a casual observer with a
friend that like they were both very
comfortable,
but then like then it turned out that it
wasn't that like safe.
So like we're on the clinical protection
side of things and we want to be really
rigorous,
but if we're not gonna be imposing fines,
I think that that ultimately gives us a
little bit more leeway to define like
what the minimums are and what the what
the constraints are.
But I back to my comment in the chat,
if we have a section for definitions like
if we can just define attended to,
right And if attended to means accessible
via video that's been consented can get
into the room like your nurse type
understanding.
I think it's worth defining those things
rather than relying on an understanding
of common knowledge,
common industry knowledge,
because this is gonna go like,
I think the people participating in this
may not be 100% aligned on vocabulary,
but I think we're in the right space with
this.
Yeah.
So what would you like change?
So what language would you prefer to use?
It's my question.
No, I think it's good.
I think it's just like, add a glossary.
OK, Yeah, maybe.
I don't know.
I like definitions.
Yeah.
We can definitely work more on
definitions at the next one.
I just don't want to have to write
language off the fly for sure.
Yeah,
some of that is just kind of like throw
that in the parking lot.
But also like if we have like a janitor
in the facility,
the janitor can't really like fill in
that gap of of absence from provider.
But like, so I don't know,
like back to like who's in attendance or
whatever.
Yeah.
But yeah, thank you, James.
Ian,
just thought on this with the language,
because we keep bouncing around on
different languages and stuff.
Patient to provider ratios, really,
The provider's not the one.
I mean, they could be a facilitator.
But in this language,
are we saying facilitator ratio?
If so,
we're saying patient to facilitator and
then the top would be patient to
facilitator.
I do like Catherine's thought of the four
to 1 is a great place to start.
We're using very challenging people.
And then you got to think about groups,
right?
When you're in a group, you know,
a four to one makes a lot of sense.
You know,
you start getting outside that group and
we start having problems about
controlling if it's people who are
challenging.
So I like where we're going with the
minimums of the four to one.
And again,
I think that no less than two on this.
We just want to be careful of the
language.
Is it 2 facilitators?
Is it 1 facilitator and an assistant?
You know, what is the DoH thinking?
As far as other licensing?
Let's say you have somebody that's a
massage therapist and they want to be
part, not necessarily a facilitator,
but they want to be part of this.
And, and so how do they get involved?
So how do we include other people?
It cannot necessarily be that 4:00 to
1:00, but they can be present.
And then the second thing too on that is
administration.
During the administration sessions,
who is actually, you know,
giving that medicine to the individuals?
You know,
there's a lot of things that go on with
that.
Does the individual take it themselves,
you know,
where they're provided a the medicine on,
you know,
in that in that ritual or that ceremonial
time, you know,
so there's some kind of thought in there.
Is the facilitator handing the the
patient the medicine?
Is the patient being handed the medicine
through somebody else?
So that's why I'm just kind of curious on
that piece on the ratios.
We got to be careful about ratios when we
put that in there.
And so I just thought I like the four to
one facilitator to patient.
I really like that.
Anything outside of that we we could say
2.
I think there just needs to be another
section there that says, you know, there,
there should be no less than two,
you know,
employees or whatever of one has to be a
facilitator and one has to be something
else present at all times during
administration sessions.
Just a thought on that.
She's already done, Cleo.
Yeah, she could go.
All right, All righty.
And Gregory has his hand up.
I saw Raymond 1st and then Greg.
Raymond, I'm so sorry I missed your hand,
guys.
So one of the things that we're all,
we're all looking like we're on the right
track here,
we need to take into consideration the
reaction from the patients.
So when it comes to facilitator to
patient ratio,
some people are going to have gastro
reactions and it's just,
it's a matter of fact.
So while the facilitator is tending to
that person's needs,
that's going to leave the other three
unattended.
So we want to make sure that we do have
the two facilitators just in case.
If you have a, a four to one ratio,
if two of them have gastro issues,
then you're going to have both
facilitators out.
We're looking at worst case scenario.
I want to, I want to look at both sides,
you know, the extremes of both.
So I think at minimum there needs to be
the two facilitators and they need to
have equal qualifications because they
need to understand exactly what's going
on in the event that the other one has to
go down the hallway with a patient to
help them, you know,
alleviate what's whatever's going on.
So they need to be equally qualified.
An assistant would be great,
but if they get in over their head
because the facilitators, you know,
in the restroom helping someone,
what's going to happen there?
So I think the, the intent here is, yes,
there the ratio can be smaller, you know,
4 to 6 I believe was something we
discussed.
But there does need to be two present.
And you know, one could be the provider.
The provider could be present because
they're going to have the, the,
the larger set of qualifications in the
event that that facilitator has to be
relieved for a short period of time.
So we're on the right track.
Just keep in mind that there are
absolutely going to be times when the
facilitator needs to be pulled from the
group because of another patient's needs
or something going on.
Maybe they need to have a separate
session with that person because they're
reacting poorly.
And we don't want to leave the other
three unattended.
We want to make sure there's always
somebody there with those patients so
they don't harm themselves or others or
they have a bad reaction.
So just some things to keep in mind.
Thank you.
And I actually really appreciate that.
So I would think it would probably be
best to say then 4:00 to 2:00.
That way we have a one to two ratio,
which is already like a pretty solid and
then say, OK, if something goes wrong,
then worst case scenario it's a one to
four.
How do is everyone feel about that?
And then Gregory was next.
I think it's for another meeting.
But I did want to echo what I heard from
James about who is authorized to handle
medicine in that set of of facilitators,
providers and assistance.
But the point that I wanted to bring up
that I think we may experience like it
may come up.
So we think we should make ourselves
aware.
Oregon has a statute,
couldn't that explicitly states practicum
students may not be left unattended with
clients during an administration session.
I don't know if I fully agree with that,
but that being something that exists,
it's definitely something that somebody
could come back and argue about later.
Oh, I like these definitions, Jorge.
Again,
going back to the framework of doula
practice,
it's very common for there to be a
midwife, an assistant midwife,
like somebody who's in training that has
certain level of like maybe they've gone
certain,
they've gone so far in the program that
they can't they can handle certain
aspects of the process.
And then doulas being outside of the
medical system,
like often times and somebody who's like
more trained in these like the legal
parameters around this,
but a midwife can definitely like defer
to a doula to handle certain situations.
And I don't know,
I don't want to be whatever.
But this isn't too far off from like that
type of context.
You know, I think shooting your pants, oh,
making having gastral issues during a
session is maybe less intense of a
requirement to deal with than what
happens during birth.
Pardon my Monday.
No worries.
Thank you, Jorge.
Great.
Thank you for all the great comments.
This is a,
this is a great discussion as always.
And I think James and,
and Greg brought up some good points and
that's why I added the definitions of
practitioner and guide.
And these definitions are within the
roles that are being that are open for
public comment that were created by the
propagation committee.
But these are definitions that were that
refer to words that will be using in the
rules.
And so those rules,
even though they're within, I'm sorry,
these definitions,
even though they're within the
propagation rules,
they will cross over into other,
other rules that other committees are
committing.
So these definitions are going to grow.
So when you pull up those rules from the
propagation committee,
you will see those definitions.
You may not see the words like, oh,
it's not using these rules,
but it will eventually in all of the
other rules.
So if that makes sense.
So with that,
you have brought some great points up
about the languages that we use and what
is a practitioner, what is a guide?
And so the guide at what I hear is folks
using as a facilitator a guide who has
completed some training,
but is different from a practitioner.
And as you can see,
that's a licensed healthcare professional.
So the practitioner overseas, the guide.
So we're talking about Medicaid and
billing and the cost.
That's what how we reduce the cost is
that there are guides there,
but the practitioner who may be readily
available to oversee the the guides and
also administering the dosage of the
medicine.
So I hope that had some clarification
with that.
Thank you.
Yes, thank you.
And then Gregory said I would love to
offer the ability to have a trusted
friend or loved one attend.
And then in the DA,
the dosage administration clinical
practice committee they have,
they are working on guidelines to allow
support people in the room as well.
No,
lesson 2 facilitators if you just if you
just need an assistant who is there to
make sure that nobody leaves out the
window they don't need special.
I would love to offer the ability to have
a trusted friend or a loved one attend.
And then Kate had a question or comment.
Yeah,
I agree that there shouldn't be fewer
than two support people, guides,
facilitators for any group.
And other than that, though,
I think 4 to 1 is an OK ratio if you have,
you know, at least two, you know,
2 guides,
but you could have a group of 12 with
three facilitators.
I mean,
in my experience that's often been about
the ratio 4 to 1 and it works OK.
But yeah, not, not fewer than two.
Perfect.
So I I went ahead and added no less than
two providers on a premises or during
group administration.
So are we still maintaining the 4:00 to
1:00 then?
Is everyone OK with that?
I mean, that's what I was thinking.
I hear no objections so we'll just go
ahead and keep it as that.
4:00 to 1:00.
And then Catherine Warnock in the chat
said I think we should caution against
having trusted friends or loved ones.
In my experience, then this happens.
The journey focus shifts from the
intended issues to being all about their
companion.
I'm not saying we shouldn't allow this,
but we need heavy education and caution
around it.
I agree.
Definitely something that preparation
will take up,
but does anyone else have anything about
patient to guide ratios or anything in
this section?
Cool.
Oh, James, Ian,
just on that language right after the
four to one,
it just says no less than two providers.
Again,
I just didn't make sure we're just using
all the same language there.
Is that what we're really meaning is 2
providers or does that 2 facilitators are
too?
Thank you, thank you.
Cool.
And then really quickly.
Room design requirements Treatment area
shall be designed to minimize risk of
injury.
No sharp edges, ligature risks.
Furniture shall be stable and non tip
breakable items minimized.
Adequate space shall be maintained to
allow for patient movement and staff
access at all times.
And then in the chat Catherine Warnock
said adequate or minimal stairs to
bathroom so restrooms should be easily
accessible.
Should we have a minimum on the number
like per patients?
And I think that's also something we'll
have to look into as far as building
codes for each municipality.
There may be something in there that we
don't are are currently are currently
aware of.
OK, again, overstepping for codes.
Perfect.
Thank you, Anne.
I just want, Ian,
I just want to address Eileen had a
question again, she asked earlier,
we missed it.
But again,
what if people want to do this outside?
Just want to add that in there.
Maybe we can circle back to that.
Yeah.
So if people wanted to do this outside,
then the room design elements would not
apply.
But the other parts like patient to guide
ratios as well as emergency preparedness,
they should still have an ability to call
911 as well as a random emergency
response plan even if they're outside we
can say.
All right,
so long as the environment does not
propose a danger to the patients or
guides.
And reasonable measures are taken to
prevent patients from There's got to be a
better way to say, running off.
OK,
so none of the room design requirements
should be construed to disallow
psilocybin and therapy.
Psilocybin assisted therapy in nature so
long as the environment does not propose
a danger to the patients or guides and
reasonable measures are taken to prevent
patients from leaving mid session.
I'm like, OK, final few things.
Environmental controls.
Temperature shall be maintained within a
comfortable and safe range.
Adequate ventilation shall be maintained.
Sound levels shall be controlled to
minimize the stress and external
disruption.
Same thing here.
None of the environmental controls should
be construed to disallow psilocybin
assisted therapy in nature.
Cool.
Anyone have any questions, comments,
concerns?
The chat is making you laugh, I'm sorry.
Environmental controls temperature shall
be maintained.
All of you good with all of that stuff.
Cool.
And then safety equipment on site
facilities shall maintain at minimum
blood pressure monitoring equipment,
pulse oximeter and basic first aid kit.
Cool questions, comments,
concerns over any part of the document.
All right.
And then we will go ahead and have a
question with guys and other participants.
Yeah, hold on.
There was a question about guides and
other participants.
Yeah, let's see first.
Looks like Ann Mets had a question
actually for Jorge.
When will DoH have proposed rules on
allowed facilities?
I know many of us are wondering what this
will look like and what will be eligible
space to work in.
Thanks.
Thank you.
And we're, we're still working on it.
We don't have a time on that yet,
but we're also working with the training
and education as well as far as
facilities and and training.
So we'll be working on those together and
the next training in education is coming
up on April 15th.
So we'll start working on that as well.
The next question,
there was another question right after
that have a question about hip compliance
with guides and other participants.
Was there a question on what was the
question?
It was Has there been a conversation
about HIPAA compliance?
Not specifically,
this would be a medical program,
so it would be reasonable that it would
apply similar to how HIPAA still applies
to the medical cannabis program.
So I don't see why ours would be any
different.
But not a specific discussion has taken
place about HIPAA.
All righty.
And with that done,
all those in favor of adopting the
environmental safety that we have gone
over today, please raise your hand.
Yeah, total of seven hands,
7 including the chair.
All right,
all those against or please lower your
hands at this time.
Perfect.
And then all those against,
please raise your hands.
I see zero at this time.
7 yes, zero.
No.
All righty that this has been adopted and
now we need to set up our next meeting
date so I can open my calendar.
We could do the 20th if that works for
everyone.
Any objections department?
You OK with that?
Yeah, that should be good.
20th at 9:00 AM that would be yes Sir.
April 20th at 9:00 AM.
And the the other that will be 420 if I'm
correct.
All righty.
Well, I will see you all happy 4:20 early.
I hope you all had a great Easter.
Thank you for showing up and spending
your morning with us.
I appreciate it.
I called this meeting of the Patient
Qualification and Safety Committee
adjourned.